Archibald MacLeish Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Literary File, 1919-1978 (Box 24-39)
  - Prose
    - Memorials Are for Remembrance, Architectural Forum, Sept. 1944
    - Mr. Nixon and the American Dream, undated
    - The Next Harvard, Atlantic Monthly, May 1941 (Box 37)
    - A Note on Alexis Saint-Léger Léger, Poetry, Mar. 1942
    - Notes on a Manifesto on Racial Equality, 12 Sept. 1944
    - Notes on the Teaching of Writing, undated
    - Now Let Us Address the Main Question: Bicentennial of What? New York Times, 3 July 1976
    - On The Irresponsibles
    - On Walter Lippmann, 1977
    - One American, undated
    - The Poems of Emily Dickinson, undated
    - Post-War Writers and Pre-War Readers, New Republic, 10 June 1940
    - The Premise of Meaning, American Scholar, Summer 1972
    - Rediscovering the Simple Life, McCall's, Apr. 1972
    - Reflections on the Occasion of Mr. MacLeish's Return From Persia, 1926
    - Return From the Excursion, undated
    - Reviews
      - Out of the People by J. B. Priestly
      - Pastoral by Robert Hillyer
      - The Ramparts We Watch
    - Riders on Earth Together, Brothers in Eternal Cold, New York Times, 25 Dec. 1968
    - Santayana, the Poet, undated
    - Silencing the Times, New York Times, 18 June 1971
    - South America III: Chile, undated
    - South America IV: The Argentine, undated
    - Sweet Land of Liberty, Collier's, 8 July 1955
    - The Swing Right, Civil Liberties, Feb. 1969
    - The Teacher's Faith, undated
    - The Third Anniversary, undated
    - A Time Without a Mirror
    - To Face the Real Crisis: Man Himself, undated
    - Topsails and Conestogas, undated
    - Tribute to John Hall Wheelock, 26 Nov. 1978
    - The Venetian Grave, Saturday Review, 9 Feb. 1974
    - Victory Without Peace, Saturday Review, 9 Feb. 1946
    - We Have Purpose, We All Know It, Life, 30 May 1960 See also Container 45, The National Purpose, June 1960
    - We've Been Pretending That We Didn't Know It's Just One World, San Francisco Chronicle, 26 Apr. 1945
    - What Is 'English'?, undated
    - Who Killed Cockrobin?, undated
    - The Women's War, Junior League Magazine, Sept. 1942 (Box 38)
    - Words Are Not Enough, Nation, 13 Mar. 1943
    - The Worn at Heart, undated
    - Yankee Skipper, Yale Review, June 1949
    - Untitled, (2 folders)
    - Printed copies, 1934-1974, undated, (3 folders)
  - Screenplays and scripts
    - The Eleanor Roosevelt Story, motion picture, 1965
      - Correspondence
      - Manuscript drafts
    - It Can't Last (Box 39)
    - John Keats
    - Magie Prison, 1967
      - Correspondence
      - Manuscript and typescript drafts
      - Miscellany
    - Morgan, Arthur, film project
    - Our Lives, Our Fortunes and Our Sacred Honors, telecast
    - The Star-Spangled Banner, recordings script for the Smithsonian Institution, 15 Feb. 1968
    - This Is Your Enemy, introduction
    - War Loan Drive script for Orson Welles, June 1944
- Speeches and Lectures File, 1939-1978 (Box 39-50)
  Handwritten and typewritten drafts, correspondence, trial lines, printed copies, notes and worksheets, outlines, proofs, and miscellaneous items relating to classroom lectures, interviews, and radio and television broadcasts.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein, except for the classroom lectures, which are arranged alphabetically by course title.
  - Classroom lectures (Box 39)
    - English
      - 180, An Approach to Poetry
      - 190
      - 283, Forms and Conditions of Modern Poetry, (1 folder) (Box 40)
    - Humanities
      - 130, An Approach to Poetry, (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 41)
      - 130a, An Approach to Poetry
      - 136
    - Chinese poetry lectures
    - John Keats lectures
    - Ezra Pound lectures (Box 42)
    - Rainer Maria Rilke lectures
    - William Butler Yeats lectures
    - Unidentified lectures and notes
  - Interviews
    - 1945
      - 5 Jan., Johannes Steele broadcast
      - 17 Jan., March of Time broadcast
    - 1952, 10 Nov., recorded interview
    - 1960, Jan., Hall, Donald, An Interview With Archibald MacLeish, Horizon
    - 1972, Mott, Ben de, interview for Paris Review
    - 1974, Oct., Heyen, William, and Anthony Piccione, A Music That Means: A Conversation With Archibald MacLeish, edited by Philip L. Gerber at Brockport Writers' Forum
    - 1975, Kressler, David J., interview for Ph.D.
    - 1976, 7 Mar., A Conversation With Archibald MacLeish, Public Broadcasting System, Bill Moyers' Journal"
  - Lectures
    - 1944, 31 May, Walgren lecture, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
    - 1947, 11 June, Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H., outline for course on Great Issues
    - 1952, July, Nashville, Tenn., on the teaching of poetry
    - 1958, Oct., Poetry and Journalism, Seymour lecture, Minneapolis, Minn.
    - 1967, 1 Nov., The Teacher and the Lively Arts, Education Council for School Research and Development (Box 43)
    - Undated
      - Holyoke Community College, Holyoke, Mass., seminar on the writer's art
      - The Language of Poetry, paper prepared for the Columbia Conference on The Unity of Knowledge
      - Human Values in the World Today Mount Holyoke College, Holyoke, Mass.
      - Poetry and the Anti-World
      - Poetry and the Arable World
  - Radio and television broadcasts
    - 1939, 26 Dec., Broadcast address on Johann Gutenberg
    - 1940
      - 16 Apr., Introductory remarks for CBS program of folk music from the Library of Congress
      - 4 May, America Was Promises, CBS broadcast See also Container 33, America Was Promises
      - 24 Nov., Art and Our Warring World, NBC broadcast
    - 1941, 13 Dec ., The Bill of Rights Now, Metropolitan Opera Program
    - 1942
      - 14 Feb., This Is War
      - 1 Mar., Propaganda: Good and Bad, NBC Broadcast
      - 14 Mar., Remarks on NBC, Inter-American University of the Air
      - 13 June, Closed circuit broadcast on gasoline and rubber shortages
      - 13 Sept., Intermission remarks on CBS Summer Symphony
      - May-June, Proposals for NBC, Inter-American University of the Air
    - 1943
      - 21 Aug., For This We Fight, NBC broadcast
      - 25 Dec ., The Meaning of Peace, Metropolitan Opera Program
    - 1944
      - 25 July, It Is What We Are, Edwin C. Hill radio program
      - 2 Dec., Remarks on the Metropolitan Opera Program
    - 1945
      - Feb.-Aug., Our Foreign Policy, NBC broadcast
        - Programs
          - 1-10
          - 11-25, (2 folders) (Box 44)
      - May-Aug., Armed Forces Radio Service programs, (2 folders)
      - 16 June, Report From San Francisco, NBC broadcast
      - 16 Dec., Can We Educate for World Peace? WGN-Mutual broadcast
      - Eulogy for Paul Valery, [1945?]
    - 1946, 25 Sept., Remarks on UNESCO, NBC broadcast
    - 1951, 30 Nov., Intermission remarks on Bernal Diaz's The True History of the Conquest of New Spain
    - 1960, 30 May, The National Purpose, WBC broadcast, See also Container 37, We Have Purpose, We All Know It, Life (Box 45)
    - 1962, 2 Aug., The Dialogues of Archibald MacLeish and Mark Van Doren, CBS telecast
    - 1976, 4 July, On the American Revolution
  - Speeches
    - 1939
      - 12 Oct., The American Experience, dedication of the Hispanic Room in the Library of Congress
      - 19 Oct., Libraries in the Contemporary Crisis, Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh, Pa.
      - 19 Nov., Remarks at the laying of the cornerstone of the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, N.Y.
      - The Freedom to End Freedom, Survey Associates
    - 1940
      - Jan., The Obligation of Libraries in a Democracy, District of Columbia Library Association
      - 22 Feb., The Librarian: His Name and Nature, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
      - 9 Apr., Writers and Scholars, American Philosophical Society
      - 31 May, The Librarian and the Democratic Process, American Library Association, Cincinnati, Ohio
      - May, Dedication of Columbus mural in the Hispanic Room of the Library of Congress
      - 10 Sept., International Student Service, International House, New York, N.Y.
      - 13 Oct., New York and Brooklyn Federation of Jewish Charities, Brooklyn, N.Y. See Container 24, The American Cause
      - 23 Oct., Forum of the New York Herald Tribune See Container 24, The American Cause
      - 19 Nov., The Duty of Freedom, Printing House Craftsmen
    - 1941
      - 12 Feb., Lincoln in This Day, Canadian Club, Ottawa, Canada
      - 3 Apr., New Land: New World, Common Council for American Unity
      - 7 June, To the Class of '41, Commencement address, Union College, Schenectady, N.Y.
      - 11 June, Prophets of Doom, Commencement address, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Penn.
      - 16 June, Commencement address, Wellesley College, Wellesley, Mass. (Box 46)
      - 19 June, Stanford University, Stanford, Calif.
      - 10 Sept., Message to P.E.N. Club, London, England
      - 10 Sept., U.S. Committee for the Care of European Children
      - 20 Nov., Council for Democracy, Boston, Mass.
      - 2 Dec., A Superstition Is Destroyed, dinner in honor of Edward R. Murrow
      - 15 Dec., Dedication of Thomas Jefferson Room in the Library of Congress
    - 1942
      - 11 Feb., Urban League
      - 13 Mar., Acceptance of death mask of Lord Lothian for the Library of Congress
      - 19 Mar., Freedom House, New York, N.Y., address
      - 14 Apr., Russian War Relief luncheon, New York
      - 17 Apr., American Society of Newspaper Editors, New York, N.Y.
      - 20 Apr., The Psychological Front, Associated Press, New York, N.Y.
      - 6 May, American Booksellers Association, New York, N.Y.
      - 11 May, What Government Asks of Broadcasters, National Association of Broadcasters, Cleveland, Ohio
      - May, The Image of Victory, Commencement address, Williams College, Williamstown, Mass.
      - 17 June, National Retail Dry Goods Association, Chicago, Ill.
      - 26 June, Toward an Intellectual Offensive, American Library Association, Milwaukee, Wisc.
      - 30 July, American Opinion and the War, Cambridge University, Cambridge, England (Box 47)
      - 15 Oct., Pour La Victorie dinner, New York, N.Y.
      - 22 Oct., Boston Book Fair, Boston, Mass.
      - 4 Dec., New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Boston, Mass.
      - 10 Dec., Dinner in honor of George W. Norris
    - 1943
      - 8 Feb., Council on Foreign Relations, Chicago, Ill.
      - Mar., The Act of the Imagination, University of California, Berkeley, Calif.
      - 28 May, The Practice of Citizenship, Commencement address, Sarah Lawrence College, Bronxville, N.Y.
      - 22 Aug., Commencement address, Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind.
      - 1 Nov., Sinai Temple Forum, Chicago, Ill.
      - 12 Dec., National Woman's Party
    - 1944
      - 24 Feb., The American Experience, American Museum of Natural History, New York, N.Y.
      - 27 Feb., Nation dinner in honor of Freda Kirchwey
      - 19 May, The Power of the Spoken Word, American Academy of Arts and Letters and the National Institute of Arts and Letters
      - 7 June, Deerfield Academy, Deerfield, Mass.
      - 28 June, Launching of the Liberty Ship Rubén Dario
      - 31 July, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisc. (Box 48)
      - 8 Oct., The People Are Indivisible, Nation conference
      - 16 Oct., Community War Fund
      - 3 Nov., Civil Service Assembly, Chicago, Ill.
      - 13 Nov., Arts, Letters and Democracy
      - 28 Nov., Freedom House, New York, N.Y., award
      - 12 Dec., Statement before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee
    - 1945
      - 4 Jan., Information for a People's Peace, United Nations Information Board
      - 10 Jan., Popular Relations and the Peace, Association of American Colleges, Atlantic City, N.J.
      - 18 Feb., The American Certainty, Independent Citizens Committee of the Arts, Sciences and Professions, New York, N.Y.
      - 28 Feb., The Problem of Developing Public Understanding of the Proposals for United Nations Organization, Americans United for World Organization
      - 3 Apr., Introductory remarks regarding the United Nations
      - 21 Apr., Americans United for World Organization and The Free World Association of Hollywood, Los Angeles, Calif.
      - 31 May, Commencement address, National College of Education
      - 7 Aug., Washington Advertising Club, Washington, D.C.
      - 27 Dec., New School for Social Research, New York, N.Y.
    - 1946, 11 Jan., National Conference of the Sciences, Professions, Arts and White Collar Fields, New York, N.Y.
    - [1953?], On The Irresponsibles, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
    - 1955
      - 16 June, Harvard Alumni Association, Cambridge, Mass.
      - 20 Nov., Commemoration of the Centennial of the death of Adam Mickiewicz, Hunter College, New York, N.Y.
    - 1956
      - 6 June, Commencement address, Smith College, Northhampton, Mass.
      - 14 June, Dinner in honor of Felix Frankfurter, Somerset Club, Boston, Mass.
    - 1958, 22 Apr., Address on J.B., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
    - 1960, 7 Oct., Yale Alumni Convocation, New Haven, Conn.
    - 1963, 22 Feb., University of the West Indies, Mona, Jamaica
    - 1965 (Box 49)
      - May, Dedication of Countway Library, Harvard Medical School, Cambridge, Mass.
      - June, Commencement address, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
      - 19 July, Memorial ceremony for Adlai E. Stevenson, United Nations, New York, N.Y.
      - 3 Dec., Address in honor of Roger Baldwin
    - 1966
      - 11 May, Pulitzer Prize awards, New York, N.Y.
      - 11 June, Poetry Center
    - 1967
      - 12 June, Lincoln Center Festival, New York, N.Y.
      - 17 Sept., Tribute to Carl Sandburg, Lincoln Memorial, Washington, D.C.
    - 1969
      - 17 May, Remarks at Leonard Bernstein's final concert as Music Director of the New York Philharmonic, New York, N.Y.
    - 1970, 3 Oct., Dedication of Hampshire College, Amherst, Mass.
    - 1972, 5 Mar., Dedication of the Eleanor Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, N.Y.
    - 1973, 7 Dec., Tribute to Mark Van Doren, American Academy
    - 1977
      - 12 Apr., Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
      - 17 Apr., Brown University, Providence, R.I.
      - 5 Oct., International Poetry Forum
    - 1978, 6 Apr., National Medal for Literature award, New York Public Library, New York, N.Y.
    - Undated
      - Art Education and the Creative Process
      - Author as Educator, Adult Education Association
      - Brandeis University, Waltham, Mass.
      - Century Association address
      - Conversation With the Moon
      - The Crisis of the Diminished Man, University of California, Berkeley, Calif.
      - Dedication of Harvard's Hellenic Center, Washington, D.C.
      - Dedication of the Robert Frost Library, Amherst College, Amherst, Mass.
      - Dedication of the Scott Library, York University, Toronto, Canada
      - Education for Citizenship
      - Eulogy for Douglas S. Moore
      - Freedom House, New York, N.Y., award
      - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. and Worcester Polytechnic Institute, Worcester, Mass.
      - Human rights award dinner
      - Monterey, Calif.
      - On Scottish pride
      - Poetry contest, Mount Holyoke College, Holyoke, Mass.
      - Recording for the Blind
      - Sarah Lawrence College, Bronxville, N.Y.
      - Tribute to John Hall Wheelock
      - Tulsa, Okla.
  - Speeches prepared for others
    - Grew, Joseph C., New Year's Day broadcast, 1 Jan. 1945
    - Ickes, Harold L., The Future Is Our Own! radio broadcast, 4 July 1940
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D.
      - 1940, 23 Oct., Campaign speech
      - 1941
        - 20 Jan., Inaugural address
        - 4 July, Independence Day address (Box 50)
        - 11 Nov., Armistice Day speech
        - 9 Dec., On preparation for war
      - 1942, 3 Feb., Statement to the Soldiers
      - 1943, Apr., Dedication of the Jefferson Memorial, Washington, D.C.
      - 1944
        - 15 Jan., Inaugural address
        - 26 Dec., State of the Union address
      - 1945
        - 1 Jan., United Nations Declaration
        - 3 Mar., Free World Congress
        - 10 Apr., San Francisco Conference, San Francisco, Calif.
    - Stettinius, Edward R.
      - 1944, Newsreel script for the State Department
      - 1945
        - 22 Feb., Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace
        - 20 Mar., Statement on the San Francisco Conference
        - 6 Apr., Americans United dinner
        - 25 Apr., United Nations Conference
    - Stevenson, Adlai E., American Legion speech, [1952]
    - Truman, Harry S.
      - 1945
        - 12 Apr., Proclamation on Franklin D. Roosevelt's death
        - Proclamation on Japanese surrender
  - Introductions and texts for poetry readings
  - Untitled and unidentified
  - Printed copies
- Subject File, 1937-1971 (Box 50-56)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, printed matter, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Commission on Freedom of the Press, The General Report (Box 50)
    - Drafts
      - Introduction
      - Chapters 1-5, (5 folders) (Box 51)
    - Miscellany
    - Outlines
    - Printed copies
  - Contemporary Historians, Inc., The Spanish Earth (film)
  - House Committee on Un-American Activities, 1948
  - Léger, Alexis Saint-Léger (Box 52)
  - Library of Congress
  - Massine, Leonide, film project
  - Mill Reef Club, Antigua
  - Office of Facts and Figures
    - Committee on War Information
    - Correspondence
    - History of the Office of Facts and Figures
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Miscellany
    - Policies and procedures
    - Project proposals
    - Publications (Box 53)
  - Office of War Information
    - Intelligence reports
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Miscellany
    - Policies and procedures
  - Perse, Saint-John See Léger, Alexis Saint-Léger
  - Pound, Ezra (hospitalization)
    - Eliot, Thomas S.
    - Eisenhower, Milton S.
    - Fang, Achilles
    - Frost, Robert
    - Furniss, Robert M., Jr.
    - Geffen, Felicia
    - Hammond, Douglas
    - Hemingway, Ernest
    - Herter, Christian A.
    - Laughlin, James
    - MacGregor, Robert M.
    - Martinelli, Sheri
    - Meacham, Harry M.
    - Miscellany
    - Moore, Arthur V.
    - Overholser, Winfred
    - Rachewiltz, Mary de
    - Rogers, William P.
    - Scheiwiller, Vanni
  - State Department
    - Correspondence
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Miscellany
    - Research documents and statements (Box 54)
  - United Nations
    - Dumbarton Oaks proposals
      - Amendments
      - Comments and suggestions
      - Miscellany (Box 55)
    - Miscellany
    - San Francisco Conference, San Francisco, Calif.
      - Charter, (2 folders)
      - Memoranda
      - Miscellany
      - Preamble to United Nations Constitution, draft
      - Report to the President
    - UNESCO (Box 56)
      - Correspondence
      - Memoranda and working papers
      - Minutes of meetings
      - Miscellany
      - Reports
  - University of the West Indies, Mona, Jamaica
- Miscellany, 1918-1972 (Box 56-57)
  Printed matter, manuscript drafts, correspondence, miscellaneous personal records, and notes.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Awards and certificates (Box 56)
  - Bibliographies
  - Biographical and genealogical papers
  - Correspondents other than MacLeish
  - Military records
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 57)
  - Notes
  - Poems other than by MacLeish
  - Power of attorney, 30 Mar. 1944
  - Printed matter
  - Skull and Bones Club handbook, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
  - Writings other than by MacLeish
    - Benco, Nancy L., Archibald MacLeish: The Poet Librarian, Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, July 1976
    - Ferrier, J. Morton, Jr., Changes in the Content and Technique of the Poetry of Archibald MacLeish, May 1938
    - Malraux, André, Le Camp de Chartres
    - Szrulyovics, Ernest, 'The Conquistador' of MacLeish
- Additions, 1926-1981 (Box 58-61)
  Diary, notebooks, correspondence, a playscript, interview transcript, and printed matter.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Correspondence, 1963-1981 (Box 58)
  - Diary, 9 Mar.-29 Apr. 1926
  - Notebooks
    - 1933-1955, (8 vols.)
    - 1968-1978, (6 vols.) (Box 59)
    - 1975-1976, (2 vols.) (Box 60)
    - Undated, (7 vols.)
  - Printed matter, Rockford College: A Retrospective Look, 1980 (Box 61)
  - Writings, Herakles playscript, undated
  - 2020 Addition
    - Interview transcript, Denis Brian interviewing MacLeish about Ernest Hemingway, 1972
Appendix: Major Works of Archibald MacLeish
1924 The Happy Marriage, and Other Poems (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin. 79 pp.)
1925 The Pot of Earth (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin. 44 pp.)
1926 Nobodaddy (Cambridge [Mass.]: Dunster House. 67 pp.)
1928 The Hamlet of A. MacLeish (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin. 45 pp.)
1930 New Found Land (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin. [52] pp.)
1932 Conquistador (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin. 113 pp.)
1933 Frescoes for Mr. Rockefeller's City (New York: The John Day Company. 28 pp.) Poems (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin. 303 pp.)
1935 Panic, a Play in Verse (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin. 101 pp.)
1936 Public Speech (New York: Farrar & Rinehart. [40] pp.)
1937 The Fall of the City (New York and Toronto: Farrar & Rinehart. 33 pp.)
1938 Air Raid (New York: Harcourt, Brace and Company. 36 pp.)
1939 America Was Promises (New York: Duell, Sloan & Pearce. 20 pp.)
1940 The Irresponsibles (New York: Duell, Sloan and Pearce. 34 pp.)
1941 The States Talking. Published in The Free Company Presents, compiled by James Boyd ([New York]: The Free Company. pp. 219-237) The American Cause (New York: Duell, Sloan and Pearce. 43 pp.)
1944 The American Story (New York: Duell, Sloan and Pearce. 231 pp.)
1948 Actfive, and Other Poems (New York: Random House. 63 pp.)
1950 Poetry and Opinion; the Pisan Cantos of Ezra Pound ([Urbana, Ill.: University of Illinois Press]. 52 pp.)
1952 Collected Poems, 1917-1952 (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 407 pp.) The Trojan Horse (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 37 pp.)
1953 This Music Crept by Me Upon the Waters (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press. 38 pp.)
1958 J.B. (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 153 pp.)
1959 The Secret of Freedom. Published in Three Short Plays ([New York]: Dramatists Play Service, 1961]. 86 pp.)
1963 The Collected Poems of Archibald MacLeish (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 417 pp.)
1965 The Eleanor Roosevelt Story (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 101 pp.)
1967 Herakles (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 91 pp.) An Evening's Journey to Conway, Massachusetts ([Northampton, Mass.: Printed at the Gehenna Press]. 20 pp.)
1968 The Wild Old Wicked Man, and Other Poems (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 45 pp.)
1971 Scratch (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 116 pp.)
1975 The Great American Fourth of July Parade (Pittsburgh, Pa.: University of Pittsburgh Press. 51 pp.)
1976 New and Collected Poems (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 493 pp.)